Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is מז mem zayin
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 47,
and we are right on target. We pick up at the last
line of מו עמוד ב, mem vav amud bet, אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, and our learning should be in the זכות zechut of the
protection and the safety and security of the חיילים Chayalim and חיילות
Chayalot and the speedy return of the hostages and the speedy end
of the war and the safety and security for all אחינו ואחיותינו
acheinu ve'achyoteinu in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael מדינת ישראל. Medinat Yisrael. All
right, we are in the middle of a whole discussion about the
קניין kinyan how it works that משיכה קונן, meshicha konan, not כסף,
kesef, debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, classic
debate where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that from the Torah it
is money that affects the קניין, kinyan, but חז"ל Chazal
overrode that or made a תקנה takanah and said that it would
be משיכה, meshicha, taking the object into one's possession, that effects the
קניין. kinyan. And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is of the opinion that
says that no, משיכה, meshicha, the physical taking possession of the object,
is what works from the Torah. We also have been seeing a
debate about the whole question about when is money, different types of
coinage, gold, silver, copper, etc., considered to be money and when is
it considered to be product, פירות, perot, and whether חליפין chalipin can
work with money, can you do the act of חליפין chalipin with
a coin and whether you can transfer coins with חליפין. chalipin. Okay,
so now we pick up last line of
מו עמוד ב, mem vav amud bet, אמר רבא אמר רב הונא,
Amar Rava amar Rav Huna, מכור לי באלו קנה ויש לו עליו
אונאה. mechor li be'elu kana ve'yesh lo alav ona'ah. If somebody says
to somebody else, ראובן Reuven says to שמעון, Shimon, sell me your
cow with this, with my handful of coins I have in my
hand, and you don't mention exactly what the amount is, however many
coins I have in my hand, that's what I'm going to pay
for the cow, and ראובן Reuven agrees, so he says that works,
it's a קניין, kinyan, and there is אונאה, ona'ah, meaning so that
sounds like it's a normal, the fact that there's אונאה ona'ah means
that we're actually understanding that the cow's being sold for a particular
dollar amount. And even though he didn't mention the dollar amount, we're
viewing this as a normal sale for a price, and if it
is too high or too low, that would be an issue of
אונאה, ona'ah, overcharging or
underpaying. That's ויש לו עליו אונאה, ve'yesh lo alav ona'ah, that's what
it means.
Now, the question is why does it work if it's only by
paying money and we know that you normally need משיכה? meshicha? So
let's contrast this to the אף על גב דלא משך כיון דלא
קפיד קנה דכי חליפין דמי, af al gav delo mashach kivan delo
kapid kana deki chalipin dami, even though ראובן Reuven did not take
the cow into his possession,
since שמעון Shimon was not paying attention to exactly, he didn't say
how much money do you have in your hand, so as far
as he was concerned, he wasn't really looking at it as a
price and equal to the amount of
money to a certain dollar amount, he was looking of it as
a type of an object, you know, whatever a handful of money
is, treating that as a type of an object and therefore it
works as a type of a חליפין. chalipin. Now, that's not a
very helpful explanation because if it truly were an object, why is
there אונאה? ona'ah? If you switch a cow for a donkey, right,
because you're not putting a price on it, you're switching one object
for another object, it doesn't go by the rules of אונאה ona'ah
of what are you charging and what's the dollar amount. So if
we are looking at this money as just an object, why is
there אונאה? ona'ah? And if there is אונאה ona'ah because we're looking
at it as payment and that there's a price, then how does,
how come you don't need to take the cow into possession? Why
do we look at it as a type of חליפין? chalipin? So
we will see that in the גמרא, Gemara, but this is contrasted
to the next position which seems more logically consistent. מכור לי באלו
קאמר ליה, mechor li be'elu ka'amar lei,
but there is אונאה, ona'ah, sorry I forgot to read that line,
because he is still saying sell me, he didn't say swap me,
he said sell me. So the language of sell allows it to
be viewed of as a sale and not a swap, and therefore
you ask was too much money paid or too little money paid,
but the fact that you didn't say the amount lets it be
looked like as
a swap and therefore you do not have to draw the cow
into your own possession. Hard to understand how those two fit together,
let's contrast it to the next opinion. רב אבא אמר אמר רב
הונא, Rav Abba amar amar Rav Huna, so רב אבא Rav Abba
says in the name of רב הונא Rav Huna a different take
on what רב הונא Rav Huna said, מכור לי באלו קנה ואין
לו עליו אונאה, mechor li be'elu kana ve'ein lo alav ona'ah, that
if you say sell me with these, it works and there's no
אונאה, ona'ah, you view it totally as a swap, like a cow
for a donkey, and in that type of a case you take
the coins and that's a חליפין, chalipin, that's object number one, and
then שמעון Shimon takes the coins and then ראובן Reuven owns the
cow. All right, and now that's, we still have to deal with
the problem that you don't use money for חליפין, chalipin, but at
least the fact that... that it works and it's a type of
a חליפין chalipin is consistent with the idea of אין לו אונאה.
ein lo onaah. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. פשיטא דמים ואין מקפיד עליהן, הכא
אמינא דקני, דכחליפין דמו. Pshita damim ve'ein makpid aleihen, hacha amina dekni,
de'kachalipin damu.
So the גמרא Gemara says it's obvious if we're dealing with a
case that there's money in your hand but you're not saying how
much it is and שמעון Shimon isn't מקפיד, makpid, isn't careful to
determine the exact amount, so then that works. That's what we're saying
is like חליפין, chalipin, it's like the money is like an object.
חליפין ומקפיד עליהן מאי? Chalipin umakpid aleihen mai? But what if, so
before we've actually fully unpacked this previous statement, we're going to ask
an analogous question. What if it is actually a swap, so we're
dealing with turning money into a swap? If you don't say exactly
the amount of money, however much money I have in my hand,
you're treating it like an object and that turns it into a
swap. Great, חליפין. chalipin. Can you do the reverse? If you have
חליפין, chalipin, a donkey for a cow, and you want to figure
out the exact price, does that change the חליפין chalipin from a
swap into a sale? So that's the גמרא's Gemara question. חליפין ומקפיד
עליהן, Chalipin umakpid aleihen, if it's a donkey and a cow but
you say wait a minute, how much is my donkey worth? How
much is the cow worth? Okay, whatever, this and that, fine, it's
the same amount, we can do a swap, is that going to
make it a sale and not a swap? Okay, מאי. mai. אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה תא שמע, Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava ta
shema, come and here. הרי שהיה תופס פרתו ועומד ובא. Harei shehaya
tofes parato ve'omed uva. So ראובן Reuven had his cow and he
was standing there in the marketplace ועומד ובא חברו ואמר לו ve'omed
uva chaveiro ve'amar lo and שמעון Shimon came and said to him,
פרתך
למה? Paratcha lama? Why are you bringing, why did you bring your
cow to the marketplace? So ראובן Reuven said to him, לחמור אני
צריך, Lachamor ani tzarich, because I need a donkey. So יש לי
חמור שאני נותן לך בפרתך Yesh li chamor she'ani noten lecha beparatcha
שאני נותן
לו. she'ani noten lo. So then שמעון Shimon said, oh perfect, I
have a donkey that I'll give you בפרתך beparatcha שאני נותן לו.
she'ani noten lo. פרתך בכמה, Paratcha bekama, בכך וכך. bekach vekach. So
he said how much is your, is your cow worth? So ראובן
Reuven said X amount. חמורך בכמה, Chamorecha bekama, בכך וכך. bekach vekach.
So then ראובן Reuven said to שמעון, Shimon, how much is your
donkey worth? בכך וכך, Bekach vekach, okay,
Y amount. Good, perfect. משך בעל החמור את הפרה. Mashach ba'al hachamor
et hapara. Now, so let's say he says fine, it's a sale,
it's a good swap, and then the
and then the the owner of the of the donkey, שמעון, Shimon,
goes ahead and he takes the cow into his possession. ולא הספיק
בעל הפרה למשוך את החמור עד שמת החמור, Velo hispik ba'al hapara
limshoch et hachamor ad shemet hachamor, and ראובן Reuven did not yet
take the donkey into his possession,
and then the donkey died. לא קנה בעל החמור את הפרה. Lo
kana ba'al hachamor et hapara. So then the sale did not go
through and שמעון Shimon did not take possession of the cow. Why?
Because it seems like somehow it went from a swap to a
sale. Since they were figuring out the exact dollar amount, it gets
considered to be a sale. Now if it's a sale, the question
is who's, which is the money and which is the object? So
it seems that since ראובן Reuven was there with the cow looking
for a donkey and he was the guy, he was coming to
the market to buy a donkey and he had his cow to
offer, that his cow was the money. So since שמעון Shimon took
the cow, that's like taking the money, and ראובן Reuven hasn't yet
taken the donkey, which is the object being sold, so there was
money given over, there was no משיכה, meshicha, the sale wasn't final,
so ראובן Reuven can back out of it. So that sounds like
that answers our question. If you start putting a dollar amount on
the objects that you're selling,
even if you're doing a swap, it's really a sale. So that's
a pretty good proof. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר
רבא. Amar Rava. So רבא Rava says. שמע מינה, Shma mina, says
the גמרא. Gemara. You can infer from this that חליפין ומקפיד עליהם
לא קנה, chalipin umakpid aleihem lo kana, that even if it's a
swap, if you're being exacting about how much it's worth, it doesn't
work. Okay, so because it's like, it's no longer like a swap,
like חליפין, chalipin, it's more like purchasing something with money. אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, so let's see how the response is. רבא Rava responded,
אטו חליפין בשוטני עסקינן דלא קפדי? Atu chalipin beshotni askinan dela kapdi?
Are we talking about idiots who do חליפין? chalipin? When you swap
something, you have to be pretty stupid to say, oh, a donkey
for a cow, great, let's swap it. People, even when they do
swaps, are not stupid in business, and they are paying attention to
whether they're getting more or less than the object they're swapping for.
Okay, so every חליפין chalipin says רבא Rava is okay that you
go ahead and you figure out exactly how much it's worth and
maybe even you pay the difference. A donkey for a, well we'll
see about paying a difference in a minute. But if you go
ahead and you pay attention to the value and you look at
it and so on, then that actually and you say okay it's
equal value let's do the swap, that is still a swap. Okay,
we don't have to assume that חליפין chalipin only works if people
are idiots. All right, so then what is this ברייתא? braita? to
the talking about and הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, what are
we talk- oh, so אלא ella rather, כל חליפין מקפד קפיד וקני.
kol chalipin mikpad kapid vekaney. Every חליפין chalipin we can assume people
are paying attention to the value and it works, it's still a
swap and as soon as you take one object into your possession,
the sale is final, the other object switches
hands. Okay, והכא במאי עסקינן, vehacha bemai askinan, what are we talking
about here? דאמר ליה חמור בפרה וטלה ומשך את הפרה ועדיין לא
משך את הטלה.
deamar leh chamor beparah vetaleh
umashach et haparah ve'adayin lo mashach et hataleh. So because you are
מקפיד makpid on it, then the question is you want to make
it equal. So let's say the case is that the donkey is
worth a hundred and the cow is only worth sixty. I don't
know, I would have guessed that a cow is worth more than
a donkey, but whatever. Okay, so he says, "Oh, how much is
your donkey? A hundred. How much is your cow? Sixty. Oh, okay,
what are we going to do to make up the difference? Oh,
okay, I'll also give you my sheep, that's worth about forty, so
the cow and the sheep for the donkey." Great. So you were
paying attention to the money but it the value, but it is
still חליפין, chalipin, it is not a sale with it's not a
normal מכר, mecher, it's still seen as a swap, but the swap
is donkey for cow and sheep. Okay, now when is that swap
complete? When you take a full set of objects, not when you
take half of of the objects that are being swapped. So therefore,
ומשך
את הפרה ועדיין לא משך את הטלה, umashach et haparah ve'adayin lo
mashach et hataleh, so שמעון Shimon took possession of the cow but
not of the sheep,
דלא הויא ליה משיכה מעליא, delo haveya leh meshicha ma'alya, okay, and
and therefore because it was not a full משיכה, meshicha, that's why
if the donkey then dies, ראובן Reuven can still back out. So
again, it's not the פשט pshat of the ברייתא. Baraita. The פשט
pshat of the ברייתא Baraita actually is is that if you're actually
setting a dollar amount to the objects being swapped, it turns it
into a מכר. mecher. But that's not what the גמרא Gemara says,
the גמרא Gemara says of course people are going to pay attention
to the value and they read the ברייתא Baraita though as once
you're paying attention to the value, it might not be A for
B, it might be one set of objects for another set of
objects, a donkey for a cow and a sheep. And in that
case, you have to take both objects for that to be taken
into possession. Of course if ראובן Reuven took the חמור, chamor, that
would also work, but one person's, you know, side of the deal,
those objects have to be all of them, you know, have to
be taken fully into possession for it to be חליפין. chalipin. Okay,
so that's just the interesting, you know, parallel. If money when you're
not paying attention to value can be a type of a swap,
a swap when you are paying attention to value is that a
type of a sale or type of a swap? And in the
end the גמרא Gemara considers determines that it is a type of
a swap. What's not being discussed is let's say he said the
donkey for the cow plus I'll owe you forty. Okay, would that
be the forty be part of the cow plus forty dollars? Would
that make it into a sale? Would that still make it into
a swap? That's a very interesting case that the גמרא Gemara is
not addressing. Okay, now let's get back to the case we turned
had about turning the money into a type of an object. אמר
מר, amar mar,
let's go back. Okay, מכור לי באלו קנה. mechor li be'elu kanah.
Sell me with this amount, you know, bundle of money without saying
how much, that works, ויש לו עליו אונאה. veyesh lo alav ona'ah.
And there is אונאה. ona'ah. Okay, and because you didn't, so it's
still money because you said מכור, mechor, sell,
and therefore you can look at whether did you overpay or underpay.
But because again you didn't say the exact amount, you're treating it
as an object and you're doing חליפין chalipin on it. Okay, so
now we have a problem which is besides that those two don't
work exactly together, right? Is it a sale or is it a
swap? But even if somehow you allow for the hybrid and you're
saying, "Okay, it's a sale but you're but it's enough you're treating
the money of an object that it lets it be like a
swap," but at the end of the day, since when can you
use money no matter how you frame it to do חליפין chalipin
with? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
לימא, leima, should we say, סבר רב הונא מטבע נעשה חליפין, savar
Rav Huna matbea na'asah chalipin, that you can use a coin to
do חליפין? chalipin? Didn't we look learn before, you know, pretty much
everybody was saying you can't use a coin to do חליפין? chalipin?
So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no. רב הונא סבר לה
כרבי יוחנן דאמר דבר תורה מעות קונות. Rav Huna savar lah keRabbi
Yochanan deamar devar Torah ma'ot konot. רב הונא Rav Huna really holds
like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, this is similar to an answer we
said before, that says מן התורה min haTorah money actually is קונה.
koneh.
So actually what's happening in this case is that it really is
a normal מכר mecher for money, which explains why there is אונאה.
ona'ah. ומפני מה אמרו משיכה קונה, umipnei mah ameru meshicha konah,
so why did they normally say משיכה meshicha is going to be
what works and overrode the דאורייתא? de'oraita? גזירה שמא יאמר לו נשרפו
חטיך בעליה. gezeirah shema yomar lo nisrefu chitecha be'aliyah.
Because if ראובן Reuven is selling שמעון, Shimon, you know, and he's
selling him bags of grain and and he takes שמעון Shimon's money,
and then the and then if that would have finalized the sale
before שמעון Shimon came into possession. of the grain, then if a
fire would break out, Reuven would not be so motivated to put
it out. He's a שומר חנם shomer chinam as long as he's
not פושע, poshea, as long as he's not negligent he's not liable
and it would be Shimon's tough luck. So they wanted to make
sure that the object was in the possession of the person buying
it before the sale would be
final, so get your object in your hands, it's not fair that
my object is in your hands and
now I'm already considered to be the owner. Okay, so that's why
they wanted to institute משיכה. meshicha. But מן התורה, min hatorah, money
really is what does it. Since that's the case, מלתא דשכיחא גזרו
בה רבנן מלתא דלא שכיחא לא גזרו בה רבנן, milsa dishchicha gozar
bah rabanan milsa delo shchicha lo gozar bah rabanan, a matter that
was common was, in normal cases, they made this override that משיכה
meshicha is going to be קונה, koneh, but in cases that are
rare and more of an exception, they allowed money to be the...
they allowed the דאורייתא de'oraisa to work on its own terms and
they allowed the money to work. Okay, which is a bizarre idea,
how do you have a system in which sometimes this is the
rule and other times that's the rule, but of course we also
know משיכה meshicha works in certain cases, הגבהה hagbaha works in others,
מסירה mesira in others. So the fact that you have different things
working in different systems isn't the worst, but still, it's a little
strange you're going to override and change the Torah system
from כסף kesef to משיכה, meshicha, but not change it in exceptional
cases. Anyway, so this case is, at least here, the point is
not just that it's rare, I mean what situation, what aspects of
it make it an exception and rare that you want to carve
out an exception is also an important question. You don't carve out
an exception of the rule just cause things are unusual. So what
makes this exceptional is the fact that the money is being treated
somewhat like an object. Okay, but now we understand how those two
positions go together. It really is a מכר, mecher, that's why there's
אונאה, ona'ah, it's really not a swap and you really are paying
for it with money, even though you don't say the amount. But
because to some degree you treat the money as an object, you
didn't say exactly how much, it was a grab bag, that makes
it enough like a swap that we actually allowed money to operate
the way money normally would operate in the Torah and we allowed
money to be the thing that would effect the קניין. kinyan. Alright,
so that's the explanation of that first opinion, that interesting hybrid opinion,
making it at least a little more consistent.
Okay, אמר ליה מר הונא בריה דרב נחמן לרב אשי. amar lei
Mar Huna brei de'Rav Nachman le'Rav Ashi. So Mar Huna said but
the second by the way version of Rav Huna is much simpler.
It just treats the whole thing, well, it's to some degree simpler,
it says there's no אונאה, ona'ah, it's treating the whole thing as
if it were an object, and that's why there's no אונאה, ona'ah,
and therefore also the קניין kinyan is finished when the money switches
hands because you're treating it as an object. Although even there, you
have to use somewhat of the answer we just gave, because even
if you look at it as an object at the end of
the day it's still money and there's no חליפין chalipin with money,
so you might have to in the end rely on this answer
we just gave that ultimately it works according to Rabbi Yochanan. But
at least it is somewhat more consistent those two positions going together,
the other version of Rav Huna. Okay, let's keep on going.
Okay,
אמר ליה מר הונא בריה דרב נחמן לרב אשי, amar lei Mar
Huna brei de'Rav Nachman le'Rav Ashi, אתון הכי מתניתון לה אנן הכי
מתניתון לה, atun hachi masnisun la anan hachi masnisun la, וכן אמר
רב הונא אין מטבע נעשה חליפין. vechen amar Rav Huna ein matbea
na'aseh chalipin. You weren't certain whether Rav Huna held whether a coin
could use חליפין chalipin or not and therefore you challenged it, does
he hold that a coin can be done in חליפין? chalipin? No
he doesn't necessarily hold that, maybe he holds like Rabbi Yochanan and
really here it's the money that's doing the קניין. kinyan. But we
actually explicitly taught when we gave the list of אמוראים Amoraim yesterday
of the אמוראים Amoraim who hold that money cannot be used in
חליפין, chalipin, our tradition is that Rav Huna was one of those
אמוראים Amoraim who explicitly said that money cannot be used in חליפין.
chalipin. And
therefore you were sort of doing it as the hypothetical, but for
us it's clear that if Rav Huna here is allowing the money
when you say this uncounted handful of money and you hand it
over and the קניין kinyan gets finished, if he's going to allow
that to work, that for us it's black and white that can't
be חליפין chalipin because for us it's clear that Rav Huna has
פסק, paskened, black and white, money is not used for חליפין. chalipin.
And the only explanation of why that works is relying on the
position of Rabbi Yochanan that ultimately מן התורה כסף קונה. min hatorah
kesef koneh. Okay, now במה
קונים, bameh konim,
now that's the end of that discussion about working with Rabbi Yochanan
and Resh Lakish, a famous debate that's going to keep on coming
up about whether מן התורה min hatorah it's כסף kesef or from
the Torah it's really taking into possession, משיכה, meshicha, and also questions
about whether the coins
can be used in חליפין chalipin and finally the question about whether
when you treat coins like an object to what degree can it
do a type of. of a חליפין khalipin function, and when you
focus on objects and you give a dollar amount, does that start
making us want to look at it more like a sale and
less like a swap, although the answer there was no. Now that
we're talking about חליפין khalipin we're going to go on to other
aspects of חליפין, khalipin, not just about coins, but other things. Let's
take a look. Okay, במה קונין, Bameh konin, what do you use
to do the קנין? kinyan? רב אמר בכליו של קונה. Rav amar
b'kelov shel koneh. You use the objects of the person purchasing. That
totally makes sense, right? Because this is a this is a type
of a swap. So even if in somehow in there are actually,
right, two types of חליפין. khalipin. There's a type of a חליפין
khalipin which is fundamentally a swap, a donkey for a cow, and
then there's another חליפין khalipin which is like a handshake, which shows
the, you know, the the like the full intent, the גמירות דעת,
gemirut da'at, to actually finalize the deal.
And and if that is based on the model of the swap,
at least that's the paradigm, even though it really functions differently, then
the idea of כליו של קונה kelov shel koneh makes sense. I
want to buy your cow, so I give you my handkerchief, you
take my handkerchief and I get your cow. That's the type of
exchange model, that sort of that makes sense. That's כליו של קונה.
kelov shel koneh. Okay, במה קונין, Bameh konin, רב אמר בכליו של
קונה. Rav amar b'kelov shel koneh. דניחא ליה לקונה דליהוי מקנה קונה
כי היכי דליגמור וליקני ליה. d'nikha leh l'koneh d'lehavi makneh koneh ki
heichi d'ligmar v'likni leh.
Okay, so so the קונה, koneh, the purchaser, me, let's say I'm
the one purchasing it. I want, right, that the,
right, if I'm buying the cow, then the person selling me the
cow, normally the focus of דעת, da'at, right? Both you both need
the דעת da'at of the מקנה makneh and the קונה. koneh. The
one who is transferring the object out of his possession and the
one who is bringing it into his possession. But you normally start
with the דעת da'at of the מקנה. makneh. The person, you know,
שמעון Shimon there who owns the cow, he's got to get it
out of his possession. He has to be מקנה makneh his cow
to me. And therefore,
the גמרא Gemara is saying is, what's going to give him the
גמירות דעת? gemirut da'at? He's the one that needs to finalize his
דעת da'at to get it out of his possession and to transfer
it to me. So דניחא ליה לקונה, d'nikha leh l'koneh, so I
the purchaser, it's good for me, דליהוי מקנה קונה, d'lehavi makneh koneh,
that the מקנה, makneh, שמעון Shimon who is giving me his cow,
he should be the one that takes possession of my handkerchief, כי
היכי דליגמור וליקני ליה, ki heichi d'ligmar v'likni leh, so he should
have גמירות דעת gemirut da'at to transfer the cow out of his
possession and that I should be the receiver, okay? Because the דעת
da'at to transfer an object starts with the מקנה makneh who's getting
it out of his possession. So for him to get the גמירות
דעת, gemirut da'at, he should be the one that receives something from
me. That's the idea. So you could say what I said before,
which is just the model of the
swap, and that's, you know, by the way, that's how we פוסקים.
pasken. We פוסקים pasken ככליו של קונה. k'kelov shel koneh. So the
easy way to remember it is it goes by the swap. You
give your handkerchief, you get from the other person their cow or
their obligation to you and so on. But the גמרא Gemara here
is saying
it based on the principle of גמירות דעת. gemirut da'at. And it's
the גמירות דעת gemirut da'at of the מקנה makneh you care for,
so he should be the one to receive the handkerchief. Okay, that's
the first opinion. רב אמר, Rav amar, that's רב. Rav. ולוי אמר
בכליו של
מקנה. v'Levi amar b'kelov shel makneh. And לוי Levi says it goes
with the כלי keli of the מקנה. makneh. שמעון Shimon who's transferring
me his cow gives me his handkerchief, I take the handkerchief and
then I get the cow, which seems a little bizarre, right? It's
all going in one direction. So the גמרא Gemara says כדבעינן למימר
לקמן. k'd'ba'inan l'meimar l'kaman. We'll explain that momentarily what the logic of
that is. אמר ליה רב הונא מדסקרתא לרבא. Amar leh Rav Huna
mi-Diskarta l'Rava. So רב הונא מדסקרתא Rav Huna mi-Diskarta said to רבא,
Rava, וללוי דאמר בכליו של מקנה, u-l'Levi d'amar b'kelov shel makneh, הא
קקני ארעא אגב גלימא? ha ka-kani ar'a agav glima? So one minute,
he says, according to לוי Levi that they're both going in the
same direction, so you are wind up purchasing land through a cloak?
Meaning, if let's say שמעון Shimon was selling me not his donkey
but his plot of land, which you can also sell by חליפין,
khalipin, so then by giving me his handkerchief, I get the handkerchief
and I get the land with it. That's a little bizarre. Okay?
והאנן קני ארעא אגב גלימא? v'ha-anan kani ar'a agav glima? אי הכי
הוי ליה נכסים שיש להם אחריות נקנין עם נכסים שאין להם אחריות.
ei hakhi havi leh nechasim she-yesh lahem achrayut niknin im nechasim she-ein
lahem achrayut.
You have property that has liens, meaning real estate, that winds up
being taken possession of through the possession of property that does not
have liens, meaning chattel. By taking possession of chattel of the handkerchief,
you're taking possession of the real estate. והאנן איפכא תנן, v'ha-anan ipcha
tnan, but our normal principle goes the exact opposite, that the more
weighty is the real estate. נכסים שאין להם אחריות נקנין עם נכסים
שיש להם אחריות. nechasim she-ein lahem achrayut niknin im nechasim she-yesh lahem
achrayut. That if you that chattel can be purchased, can be taken
possession of through taking possession of land. If I want to sell
you this plot of land plus my car, by taking possession of
the land you can if that's if the deal was that you'll
get both, then by when you take possession of the land you
also get the car, but you can't take the car and through
it get the land, okay? Land drags the chattel with it, not
the reverse. But here he's saying the chattel, the handkerchief is dragging
the land with it. So that seems like an excellent question. Let's
see what the response is. אמר ליה Amar lei Rava said back
to him אי הוי לוי הכא ei havi Levi hacha if Levi
was here הוי מפקי לאפך פולסי דנורא havi mappik l’appach pulsei d’nura
he would take out in front of you rods of flame and
like to beat you with them. He would be so angry that
you had challenged him with this question. מי סברת Mi savrat גלימא
מקני ליה glima maknei lei but
what makes you think that what he's doing is he's selling him
the cloak, meaning I'm going to sell you the cloak and by
taking possession or give you the cloak and by taking possession of
the cloak, you'll take possession of the plot of land. That's not
the conceptual model we're dealing with here. Okay, what's the model? Here's
the model. בההיא הנאה דקמקבל מיניה Be'hai hana'ah d’kamakabbel minei גמר ואקני
ליה. gemar v’akni lei.
No,
what it is is because I'm getting benefit that you are agreeing
to accept something from me, we sometimes have that in the גמרא
Gemara that there can be an idea that the one who is
giving the gift gets benefit from the fact that, you know, that
the receiver agreed to accept the gift. So from the fact that
you that שמעון Shimon says to me, the fact that you have
accepted my handkerchief, that gives me, I'm receiving something, I'm receiving that
benefit, that honor that you דב Dov did to me by accepting
my handkerchief, and that benefit that I now receive, that is giving
me the גמר דעת gemar da'as to transfer to you my land.
So it's not that you דב Dov are purchasing the land through
taking possession of the handkerchief, rather by me receiving the benefit by
שמעון Shimon receiving the benefit of my accepting a gift, that is
the mechanism that then gives him the גמר דעת gemar da'as to
transfer the land to me. All right, it's still very convoluted, even
though it doesn't have the technical problem of acquiring land through chattel,
but to say that that is always the case that the one
selling it gets benefit that I received his handkerchief and why not
just do it the more natural way of כליו של קונה, kelyo
shel koneh, which actually is the פסק, psak, but still it's a
strange position כליו של מקנה. kelyo shel makneh. Let's take a look
as the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, כתנאי. Kitnayei. This question of do you use the object of
the קונה koneh or of the מקנה makneh is based on a
debate of תנאים. Tannaim. וזאת לפנים בישראל על הגאולה ועל התמורה לקיים
כל דבר. V’zos l’fanim b’Yisrael al ha’geulah v’al ha’temurah l’kayeim kol davar.
This is of course the פסוק passuk by רות, Rus, which is
the basis of this חליפין chalupin thing and this is in the
past in ישראל Yisrael when it comes to redemption and exchange to
establish every matter. שלף איש נעלו ונתן לרעהו Shalaf ish na'alo v’nasan
l’rei’eihu and you take off your נעלו na'alo normally translated as shoe,
but some actually suggest that it could also mean your glove and
you give it to your friend and that is the the act
of חליפין. chalupin. Okay, now that does sound by the way not
like the swap חליפין, chalupin, but it sounds like if it's always
the same thing, we talk about a handkerchief here you're talking about
a shoe, it sounds like it's this formal ritual act that shows
גמר דעת gemar da'as that just establishes a you know is the
way that you seal a deal, which is actually what the פסוק
passuk in רות Rus is saying. This is what you do לקיים
כל דבר. l’kayeim kol davar. Here's how you seal a deal, you
just give something to somebody. All right, so that's the classic חליפין
chalupin not out of a swap but the classic חליפין chalupin of
like of a גמר דעת. gemar da'as.
So so now we're going to unpack this פסוק. passuk.
Okay,
ונתן לרעהו. v’nasan l’rei’eihu. גאולה זו מכירה Geulah zu mechira וכן הוא
אומר לא יגאל. v’chen hu omer lo yiga'el. Okay, גאולה Geulah is
redemption is sale and it says it shall not be redeemed. Now
that is very strange because that פסוק passuk actually speaks about if
something is sold it should not be redeemed and contrasts redemption to
sale. תוספות Tosafos tries to say maybe it's talking about a different
פסוק passuk about מעשר שני ma'aser sheni where it might actually refer
to a type of a sale but it's a little unclear to
see what the גמרא Gemara is saying that, I mean not just
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni but מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. But we'll I'll
go back to this in a second and give a very nice
reading of this according to רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam.
תמורה זו חליפין. Temurah zu chalupin. תמורה Temurah is exchange וכן הוא
אומר לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר אותו. v’chen hu omer lo yachalifenu v’lo
yamir oso. You shall not swap it and you shall not exchange
it. All right, so so what does that mean? That means it's
two types of ways of doing חליפין. chalupin. One is you know
I'll sell me your plot of land you know for I don't
know a million dollars or sell me your cow or your donkey
and in order to finalize the sale, I give you a handkerchief
like we've been talking, a formal act and I go ahead and
I purchase, I purchase what what you were selling me. All right,
so actually it's not a swap, it's a purchase, it's a מכירה,
mechira, but it's finalized not through taking possession of the object, but
through this act of חליפין. chalifin. So חליפין chalifin can use one
way in a context of a מכירה, mechira, and it can be
used another way in a context of an exchange, a cow for
a donkey and so on. Two types of חליפין. chalifin. Okay, לקיים
כל דבר, lekayem kol davar,
in order to establish anything, שלח איש נעלו ונתן לרעהו, shalach ish
na'alo venatan lere'ehu, so it's not interpreting לקיים כל דבר, lekayem kol
davar, we have sale and an exchange. And now it says מי
נתן למי? mi natan lemi? And now we get to the question
of who's giving to who? בעז נתן לגואל. Boaz natan lego'el.
So the תנא קמא tanna kamma says בעז Boaz is giving it
to the redeemer. And רבי יהודה אומר גואל נתן
לבעז. Rabbi Yehuda omer go'el natan leBoaz. The redeemer is giving it
to בעז, Boaz, and that's the question of כליו של קונה kelav
shel koneh and כליו של מקנה. kelav shel makneh. Now who's the
קונה koneh here and who's the מקנה? makneh? So in case that
wasn't clear, you know, the ר"ח Rach says that רב Rav who
says כליו של קונה kelav shel koneh is like the תנא קמא.
tanna kamma. The תנא קמא tanna kamma that בעז Boaz is the
one who gave to the גואל go'el because he is בעז Boaz
is the קונה. koneh. He is getting רות, Ruth, the land, the
right to redeem, so he's the קונה, koneh, so that's the position
that כליו של קונה. kelav shel koneh. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that says it's the כליו kelav of the גואל go'el was the
one who gave it, it's כליו של מקנה. kelav shel makneh. Now
I want to pause for a moment and just say רבינו תם's
Rabbeinu Tam read because רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam actually, if you take
a look at תוספות גאולה, Tosafot Geulah, he says like this: and
the end of that
תוספות: Tosafot: ומפרש רבינו תם גאולה זו מכירה ולרבי יוחנן גאולה בכסף
וריש לקיש במשיכה.
umefaresh Rabbeinu Tam geulah
zo mechira ul'Rabbi Yochanan geulah bekessef veReish Lakish bemeshicha.
You know what, actually forget that, that's actually he tries to fit
in there, you know, a type of a sale without חליפין chalifin
but that actually is a harder read of the פסוק. pasuk. But
he's trying to also do the three parts of the פסוק, pasuk,
the part the גמרא Gemara did not address which was לקיים כל
דבר. lekayem kol davar. If you ask me what the לקיים כל
דבר lekayem kol davar could be is a type of a way
that חליפין chalifin is also used not for transfer but for התחייבות,
hitchayvut, for obligation. So for example think about the כתובה. ketubah. Okay,
in the case of the כתובה ketubah the rabbi who represents the
כלה kallah gives the handkerchief or the whatever the watch to the
חתן. chassan. The חתן chassan accepts it and through accepting it he
is obligating himself to the כלה kallah with all the obligations in
the כתובה. ketubah. So that's a real first of all it's כליו
של קונה. kelav shel koneh. The חתן chassan is the one who's
obligating himself. And the rabbi just represents the כלה. kallah. And it
is לקיים כל דבר, lekayem kol davar, you're not swapping, you're not
selling, you're התחייבות. hitchayvut. So that actually is a nice way to
read it, interestingly the גמרא Gemara did not pull that out. Okay
let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר רב נחמן לא שנו אלא בכלי... Amar Rav Nachman lo shanu
ella bikli... I'm sorry I skipped a line. תנא, Tanna, we taught
in a ברייתא, braita, קונין בכלי אף על פי שאין בו שווה
פרוטה. konin bikli af al pi she'ein bo shaveh pruta. You the
קניין kinyan is with a כלי kli like a נעלו, na'alo, a
type of a functional object, even though it is not worth a
פרוטה. pruta.
And that's why you could do it by a handkerchief or whatever,
it doesn't even have to be worth a פרוטה. pruta. The emphasis
is it's some object. אמר רב נחמן לא שנו אלא בכלי אבל
בפירות לא. Amar Rav Nachman lo shanu ella bikli aval befeirot lo.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says only a vessel,
you cannot use fruit.
And תוספות Tosafot explains and from context it's clear what the גמרא
Gemara understands that he's saying that if it's not that fruit has
to be worth a פרוטה, pruta, you can't use fruit at all.
You can only use a כלי kli and that can be less
than a פרוטה pruta but you can't use something like you know
something that's consumable and not made to be functional. So fruit, food
and so on. That you cannot use.
ורב ששת אמר אפילו בפירות. veRav Sheshet amar afilu befeirot. Even fruit.
מאי טעמא דרב נחמן? Mai ta'ama deRav Nachman? What's the reasoning of
רב נחמן? Rav Nachman? אמר קרא נעלו. Amar kra na'alo. נעל אין,
מידי אחריני לא. Na'al in, midi achrini lo. Because it's the פסוק.
pasuk. It says you know his shoe, so it has to be
something like a shoe, it has to be a man-made you know
functional object.
מאי טעמא דרב ששת? Mai ta'ama deRav Sheshet? And if you know
it's a question about גמירת דעת gemarat da'at and something of significance
and we're not fundamentally starting with the model of a swap, you
know, that makes a lot of sense. What's the reasoning of רב
ששת? Rav Sheshet? אמר קרא לקיים כל דבר Amar kra lekayem kol
davar because it says for to establish everything. Now just because it
says כל דבר, kol davar, that's what it's effecting, that doesn't mean
what the act is done with, but רב ששת Rav Sheshet reads
that to say the כל דבר kol davar it can be done
with anything. לרב
נחמן נמי הא כתיב לקיים כל דבר? LeRav Nachman nami ha ktiv
lekayem kol davar? So what does רב נחמן Rav Nachman who limits
the objects do with לקיים כל דבר? lekayem kol davar? הוא לקיים
כל דבר דניקנין במינו. Hu lekayem kol davar diniknin bimino. That means
that you can you have to use a כלי kli but you
can be קונה koneh anything you want with it which is certainly
the פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. ורב ששת נמי הא כתיב
נעלו? veRav Sheshet nami ha ktiv na'alo? So רב ששת Rav Sheshet
what does he do with the word נעלו na'alo that seems to
limit the type of objects you can use? אמר לך רב ששת,
Amar lecha Rav Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet would say to you:
מה נעלו דבר... ma na'alo davar... מה נעלו דבר מסוים אף כל
דבר מסוים לאפוקי חצי רימון וחצי אגוז דלא. ma na'alo davar mesuyam
af kol davar mesuyam l'afokei chatzi rimon v'chatzi egoz d'lo. Okay, now
lo means this has to be like something complete. It can't be
half of an apple. It does have to have significance and חשיבות,
chashivut, but that חשיבות chashivut does not have to be the significance
of being a כלי, kli, it could even be food, but it
has to be something, a full thing and not a half of
a thing. All right, אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, said רב
ששת Rav Sheshet בריה דרב אידי, breih d'Rav Idi, כמאן כתבינן האידנא,
k'man kasvinan ha'idna, okay, according to which halakhic positions do we... are
reflected by the language we use in a standard document of a
sale or of a התחייבות hitchayvut of an obligation. What's the language?
במנא דכשר למקניא ביה, B'mana d'chasher l'miknya bei, if anybody who listens
when they read the כתובה, ksuva, that's what it says at the
end. וקנינא מן V'kanina min whatever במנא דכשר למקניא ביה, b'mana d'chasher
l'miknya bei, we acquired from the חתן, chosson, you know, meaning we
took possession, we were the receivers of his obligations to the כלה,
kalla, that's what it means, using this vessel that it's fit to
do a קנין kinyan with, you know, והכל שריר וקיים. v'hakol sharir
v'kayam. So במנא, b'mana, so what does it mean? ביה, bei, במנא
דכשר למקניא ביה. b'mana d'chasher l'miknya bei. במנא B'mana with a כלי
kli לאפוקי מרב ששת l'afokei miRav Sheshet דאמר קונין בפירות d'amar konin
b'peiros to reject the רב ששת's Rav Sheshet position that says you
do it with fruit. No, we explicitly emphasize that it's a כלי.
kli.
דכשר D'chasher that it's appropriate to be קונה koneh with,
לאפוקי משמואל l'afokei miShmuel to reject שמואל's Shmuel position דאמר קונין במרוקא.
d'amar konin b'maroka. You can use מרוקא maroka as the vessel to
do the קנין. kinyan. What is מרוקא? maroka? So רש"י Rashi says
that it's some type of a vessel made from dung. תוספות Tosafos
says it's made from some type of a pits of a date.
But something that's considered to be inappropriate. I don't know exactly how
you measure inappropriate, but you know, something that's considered to be disgusting
and lowly.
Okay. למקניא, L'miknya, so that's במנא דכשר b'mana d'chasher appropriate למקניא l'miknya
to be
קונה koneh with לאפוקי מדלוי l'afokei mi'deLevi דאמר בכליו של מקנה d'amar
b'keilav shel makneh קמשמע לן kamashma lan למקניא l'miknya ולא לקנויי ביה.
v'lo l'aknuvei bei. So למקניא l'miknya means that it's fit to acquire
with it and that's the Aramaic, למקניא l'miknya means to acquire with,
we use the vessel through giving this handkerchief to the חתן, chosson,
that was a vessel that was appropriate for us, it we did
it with a vessel for us to be קונה, koneh, take possession,
or for the עדים edim or the rabbi to take the accept
the obligations on behalf of the כלה. kalla. So למקניא l'miknya means
to acquire,
and
if it was the מקנה makneh it would have said לקנויי l'aknuvei
ביה bei to transfer possession. Okay. And so קמשמע לן kamashma lan
I'm sorry, לקנויי l'aknuvei excuse me, למקניא l'miknya is to take possession.
Okay, the Hebrew and the Aramaic mix me up. קמשמע לן Kamashma
lan למקניא l'miknya to take possession, we are using this handkerchief to
take possession, ולא לקנויי ביה v'lo l'aknuvei bei and not to transfer
ownership. So it's the כלי kli of the
קונה. koneh. Okay. Now ביה, v'bei, what is ביה bei coming to
do? רב פפא אמר למעוטי מטבע. Rav Pappa amar l'ma'utei matbea. That's
excluding a coin.
Not exactly clear how the word ביה, bei, but it's another excluding
word, so it's excluding a coin. All right, which is our previous
discussion. ורב זביד ואיתימא רב אשי אמר למעוטי איסורי הנאה. V'Rav Zevid
v'isayma Rav Ashi amar l'ma'utei issurei hana'ah. Now, to exclude something that
is you cannot derive benefit from. Like let's say I don't know,
you know, let's say you tried to do it with בשר בחלב,
basar b'chalav, which is אסור assur to derive benefit from. Well actually
that's פירות, peiros, but let's say you fashioned, you know, some thing
out of a כלי kli out of עבודה זרה avodah zarah or
something. So even though it doesn't have to be worth a פרוטה,
pruta, it has to be something that is considered has value and
can be benefited from. Something that's out of the world of benefit,
that's not that's not appropriate to use at all. Okay.
רב זביד ואיתימא רב אשי אמר למעוטי איסורי הנאה. Rav Zevid v'isayma
Rav Ashi amar l'ma'utei issurei hana'ah. So two different interpretations. איכא דאמרי
Ika d'amri ביה bei
אמר רב פפא למעוטי מטבע amar Rav Pappa l'ma'utei matbea דכשר. d'chasher.
Okay, that ביה bei רב פפא Rav Pappa is saying with it
is coming like to exclude, excuse me, I read דכשר, d'chasher, that
didn't make sense. רב פפא אמר למעוטי מטבע. Rav Pappa amar l'ma'utei
matbea. So ביה bei רב פפא Rav Pappa is the one is
says to exclude a coin, which is what he said before, that
ביה bei excludes a coin. דכשר, D'chasher, going back to the word
דכשר, d'chasher, okay, אמר רב זביד ואיתימא רב אשי למעוטי איסורי הנאה.
amar Rav Zevid v'isayma Rav Ashi l'ma'utei issurei hana'ah. So that's where
it's excluding איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, so there's not a debate. Everybody
agrees that a coin is excluded and איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah is
excluded. What about the fact that we also excluded, you know, this
מרוקא maroka before, how are we going to exclude it here? So
the גמרא Gemara says אבל מרוקא לא אצטריך, aval maroka lo itzterich,
מרוקא maroka you don't even need a פסוק pasuk to exclude, it's
clearly something that's so disgusting and inappropriate that it obviously... Obviously would
not be usable for this. I don't know why that's more obvious
than איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, but okay. Anyway, that is the bottom
line is we פוסקין pasken כלי של קונה kli shel koneh and
we פוסקין pasken that you can't do it with a with a
מטבע matbe'a and we פוסקין pasken that you can't do it with
פירות. peros. Now I want to say one last thing about פירות,
peros, which is the position of רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. Because you
know the גמרא Gemara before that we did yesterday about the מי
שור mei shor etcetera was a confusing גמרא, Gemara, but without going
back to it, the basic גמרא Gemara at least the way רש''י
Rashi read it sounded like if פירות peros don't work, then you
can't do the classic cow for donkey which in most of our
minds is the classic קנין חליפין. kinyan chalipin. And that's certainly what
the גמרא Gemara as we had in our גירסא girsa read like.
But תוספות Tosafot there presents a whole different גירסא girsa and he
presents the position of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam that you can swap
a cow for a donkey and he says that that actually is
that those are considered to be a fit in the כלי. kli.
You use a cow and a donkey so even though they're not
man-made, they are a כלי. kli. They're not consumed like פירות peros
are. So that's point number one. Point number two, and this is
really why I wanted to see the תוספות Tosafot I started reading
before, is that רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam separates the two types of
חליפין. chalipin. One is when you're actually doing it like a handkerchief,
right, לקיים כל דבר, lekayem kol davar, or על המכירה, al hamachira,
you're trying to sell something or obligate yourself with something. It's not
a swap. Those are the places he says you have these formal
rules that has to be, you know, כלי של קונה kli shel
koneh and it has to be only a כלי kli and it
can't be food. We can debate whether animals are in the כלי
kli category or the food category. That's when it is לקיים כל
דבר lekayem kol davar or על הגאולה al hage'ulah which means sale.
But when it's על התמורה, al hatemurah, an exchange, you know, like
apples for oranges, a donkey for a cow, there רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam says everybody would agree that פירות peros actually work. Because there
you're not using it as a formal act, you're doing an actual
exchange of items and there there is none of these restrictions of
כלי הראוי לקנות בו kli hara'uy liknot bo and all of that,
that that would not apply when you are doing an actual swap.
Very important position of רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, two very different types
of חליפין. chalipin. Okay, let's take a look now at the next
גמרא. Gemara. אסימון קונה את המטבע. asimon koneh et hamatbe'a. And אסימון,
asimon, you know, which any of
us who lived in Israel for a while going back decades remember
that the אסימון asimon were those coins that you put in the
in the payphone. So we'll see what the גמרא Gemara says it
means, but it's some type of a coin that's not a normal
standard usable coin. And that is considered to be פירות, perot, you
know, the object vis-a-vis something that is a standard coin. So if
you're paying normal bills, you know, normal coins for this אסימון, asimon,
when the person takes possession of the אסימון, asimon, then that's משיכה,
meshikha, then the קנין kinyan is final and then, you know, he
owes the money. So that's the phrase of קונה את המטבע. koneh
et hamatbe'a. The אסימון asimon is the object and the מטבע matbe'a
is the money. מאי אסימון? mai asimon? What's an אסימון? asimon? אמר
רב, amar Rav, מעות הניתנות בסימן לבית המרחץ. ma'ot hanitanot besiman leveit
hamerchatz. It's money that was maybe, you know, out of circulation, wasn't
really used, and you would give it as a type of an
indicator, like as a type of a what's the word a chit.
You would give it as a chit to the guy standing at
the at the bathhouse. So, you know, he was counting how many
people went in or maybe you gave him a chit and then
he knew, I don't know, he'd give you a towel, who knows
what it would be, you know, but some way of keeping track
of something but not actually used to purchase. Okay, and it's not
real, really used as money. מכלל, mikhlal, says the גמרא, Gemara, דאסימון
לאו de'asimon lav I'm sorry. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
מיתיבי, meitivei, I
ask you on this: אין מחללין מעשר שני על אסימון, ein mechalelin
ma'aser sheni al asimon, you cannot redeem מעשר שני ma'aser sheni on
an אסימון, asimon, ולא על מעות הניתנות בסימן לבית המרחץ, velo al
ma'ot hanitanot besiman leveit hamerchatz, and not money that's given as a
chit as the type in the bathhouse. מכלל, mikhlal, so if it
says two things, דאסימון לאו מעות הניתנות בסימן לבית המרחץ, de'asimon lav
ma'ot hanitanot besiman leveit hamerchatz, clearly the אסימון asimon is not what
you just described it as. That's a separate thing. וכי תימא פירושי
קמפרש, vekhi teima perushei kamfaresh, and let's say you want to say
no, no, it's explaining itself. Don't give it as an, you can't
do it on an אסימון, asimon, what's an אסימון? asimon? This thing
given in the בית המרחץ. beit hamerchatz. והלא תנא הכי, vehalo tana
hakhi, but we didn't teach that way, we clearly recognized it as
two separate things. Why? Because here's what we taught in the משנה.
mishna.
מחללין מעשר שני על אסימון, mechalelin ma'aser sheni al asimon, you can
transfer מעשר שני ma'aser sheni onto an אסימון, asimon, דברי
רבי דוסא, divrei Rabbi Dosa, that's what Rabbi Dosa says. וחכמים אומרים
אין מחללין, vachachamim omrim ein mechalelin, you can't.
ושוין שאין מחללין על מעות הניתנות בסימן לבית המרחץ, veshavin she'ein mechalelin
al ma'ot hanitanot besiman leveit hamerchatz, but they all agree you can't
do it on money given in the בית המרחץ. beit hamerchatz. Okay,
clearly an אסימון asimon is debated and the בית המרחץ beit hamerchatz
money is not, so clearly it is something different. So what is
it? אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, ela amar Rabbi Yochanan, מאי אסימון? mai
asimon? פולסא. pulsa. What is an אסימון? asimon? It's פולסא. pulsa. Now
that's very helpful, so what is פולסא? pulsa? So if you look
at רש''י Rashi right at the beginning of the narrow lines, רש''י
Rashi says מחוסר צורה mechusar tzurah that It is money that is
not stamped. Now remember, their money there did have was precious metal,
so it definitely was a value, but it is yet to be
stamped and therefore it's not going to be treated as normal currency.
Okay, so that makes a lot of sense. ואמר רבי יוחנן לטעמיה,
V'amar Rabbi Yochanan l'taimei, Rabbi Yochanan goes according to his reasoning, דאמר
רבי יוחנן רבי דוסא ורבי ישמעאל אמרו דבר אחד. d'amar Rabbi Yochanan
Rabbi Dosa v'Rabbi Yishmael amru davar echad. Rabbi Dosa who says you
can't use an אסימון asimon and Rabbi Yishmael follow the same reasoning.
רבי דוסא הא דאמרן, Rabbi Dosa ha d'amran, and Rabbi Dosa what
we said. רבי ישמעאל מאי היא? Rabbi Yishmael mai hi? What's Rabbi
Yishmael? דתניא דתנן בברייתא וצרת הכסף בידך, Detanya detnan b'raisa v'tzarta hakesef
b'yadecha, you shall bind the money into your hand, לרבות כל דבר
הניצר ביד דברי רבי ישמעאל. l'rabos kol davar hanitzar b'yad divrei Rabbi
Yishmael. Rabbi Yishmael saying that's coming to include anything that you can
bind into your hand. It's coming to include the objects you can
do a redeem מעשר שני maaser sheni on. רבי עקיבא אומר לרבות
כל דבר שיש עליו צורה. Rabbi Akiva omer l'rabos kol davar sheyesh
alav tzura. Rabbi Akiva says no, it's coming to say that you
can only do it on things that have an image, only on
stamped coins, not on unstamped coins that don't have an image. So
Rabbi Yishmael, who does not say the same as Rabbi Akiva, he
obviously would be more inclusive and say that if you could bind
up these if this is also precious metal, even if it doesn't
have a stamped image, you can use מעשר שני maaser sheni for
it. And Rabbi Yochanan is saying that idea that you don't need
a stamped image, that idea of Rabbi Yishmael is the same position
of Rabbi Dosa who says that you can transfer מעשר שני maaser
sheni on an אסימון. asimon. So from there it's clear that Rabbi
Yochanan understands that what is an אסימון, asimon, it is money that
does not have a stamped image on it. Okay. כיצד? Keitzad? Now
moving on. כיצד משך הימנו פירות ולא נתן לו מעות אינו יכול
לחזור. Keitzad mashach heimenu peiros v'lo nasan lo maos eino yachol lachzor.
So now the next as the משנה Mishnah speaks about if
you take the fruit even before the other person,
even before the money was paid, that finalizes a sale. But if
the money was paid and the object wasn't taken in possession, the
sale isn't final, but if you back out, you get this מי
שפרע Mi Sheparah curse. All right, so now we are going to
finally have the debate of Rabbi Yochanan and Resh Lakish in its
original location. Before, we were just citing it. Here's where this debate
is actually anchored. So אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, because from
the משנה Mishnah it's clear that when you do a sale and
one side gives money and the other side takes possession of the
object, that the sale is complete when the object is taken possession
of. That משיכה meshicha is קונה koneh and not money. And now
we're going to find out why that's the case.
ואמר רבי יוחנן דבר תורה מעות קונות. V'amar Rabbi Yochanan devar Torah
maos konos. Actually, it's the paying of money that effects the sale.
ומפני מה אמרו משיכה קונה? Umipnei mah amru meshicha konah? So why
did the rabbis override that and say משיכה meshicha is what's קונה?
koneh? גזירה שמא יאמר לו נשרפו חטיך בעליה. Gzeira shema yomar lo
nisrefu chittecha ba'aliyah. What I said before, which is that the seller
shouldn't say, "Oh, you know, a fire broke out," and even if
maybe he's lying, but even if he's not lying, he's not going
to try his best to protect your object. If you owned this
object, you should be having it in your possession before in order
that it's now your responsibility to protect it and not that somebody
else is controlling the object that you just bought. All right, so
that's why we wanted it to only work once you, the purchaser,
took possession of the object. סוף סוף, Sof sof, says the גמרא,
Gemara, מאן דשדי דליקה בעי שלומי? man deshadi delika bei shalumei? So
the גמרא Gemara says, well, why is that a problem?
So what if it burnt down? Let the guy who set the
fire pay back the purchaser. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא גזירה
שמא תפול דליקה באונס. Ela gzeira shema tipol delika b'oness. No, maybe
nobody is liable. Maybe a lightning struck, fire breaks out without anybody
being liable. So and that's the problem. אי מוקמת להו
ברשותיה, Ei mokmas lehu birshusei, if you go ahead and say that
it's in the possession still of the seller, meaning if the seller
still owns the hay in his loft even though he took the
money, מסר נפשיה טרח ומציל, masser nafshia tarach u'matzil, he's going to
really work to save it. Okay, because he doesn't want his hay
to get lost. He knows if the hay burns down, the sale
isn't final, the purchaser will back out. So as long as the
sale isn't final, he's going to really work to protect this object.
ואי לא, V'ei lo, but if you said that the purchaser already
owns the grain or the hay, לא מסר נפשיה טרח ומציל, lo
masser nafshia tarach u'matzil, he's going to not work to try to
save it. So בקיצור, bekitzur, you want
the person who owns the object should be in possession of the
object or else people will be irresponsible. That makes a lot of
sense. Okay, so that's a תקנה דרבנן. takana d'rabbanan. Now one, of
course, might want to ask what was the תורה Torah thinking that
the תורה Torah did it by כסף? kesef? It just shows an
interesting idea. Is the תורה Torah maybe society the realities of society
were different, maybe the תורה's Torah הלכה halacha of כסף kesef was
more fitting some type of
a philosophical structure that made sense, but not necessarily that it would
be the best in terms of how society actually operates. A lot
of interesting things to philosophize about here. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
has no hesitation saying that for practical. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish
Lakish* אמר משיכה meshikha. מפורשת מן התורה min haTorah *amar meshikha meforashes
min haTorah*.
No, משיכה meshikha. *meshikha* is explicit, it comes from the תורה Torah
*Torah* that that משיכה meshikha *meshikha* is what is קונה koneh *koneh*
and not money. Okay. Now, מאי טעמא דריש לקיש *mai ta'ama deReish
Lakish*, now if he said it's in the תורה Torah *Torah*, right,
so where does he see that from the תורה Torah *Torah*? אמר
קרא *Amar kora*, וכי תמכרו ממכר לעמיתך או קנה מיד עמיתך *vechi
simkeru mimkar la'amisecha o kano miyad amisecha*, if you sell a sale
to your friend or you purchase. So קנה מיד *kano miyad* from
the hand. דבר הנקנה מיד ליד *Davar hanikneh miyad leyad*. It means
that when you take it from the hand, acquisition has- comes from
the transferring it from his hand to yours. It's a little funny
because the פסוקים *psukim* are talking about land and not chattel, but
okay. It's also that those פסוקים *psukim* are talking about אונאה *ona'ah*,
overcharging and undercharging, which also according to חז"ל *Chazal* only apply to
chattel even though the פסוקים *psukim* are talking about land. So that's
just bizarre that so many things in those פסוקים *psukim* we read
about chattel even though the case itself is talking about land. But
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish, *Reish Lakish* says since it says מיד *miyad*,
it means the transfer from one hand to the next. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan אמר *Rebbi Yochanan amar*, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan*
would say, מיד למיעוטי קרקע דלית ביה אונאה *miyad lemi'utei karka deleis
bei ona'ah*. No, מיד *miyad* is coming to say as I just
mentioned that this pro- the פסוקים *psukim* there that are talking about
אונאה *ona'ah*, not overcharging, that that is only applying to chattel and
not to land. Land there is no הלכה halacha *halacha* around or
there's no consequence of overcharging. Okay, we won't go into that right
now. That'll come up next פרק *perek*. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish, *Reish
Lakish*, what does ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* say back? אם כן *Im
kein*, לכתוב קרא וכי תמכרו ממכר מיד עמיתך *lichtov kora vechi simkeru
mimkar miyad amisecha* or ליד עמיתך *leyad amisecha* אל תונו *al tonu*.
או קנה למה לי *O kano lama li*? Why does it say
וכי תמכרו ממכר לעמיתך או קנה מיד *vechi simkeru mimkar la'amisecha o
kano miyad*? Why doesn't it just say about selling it to somebody?
Why does it say purchasing it, קנה מיד *kano miyad*, from the
person's hand? That's coming to tell you that we're not just talking
about objects that are transferable but that the קנין *kinyan*, the קנה
*kano*, only works when it is מיד *miyad*, when it goes out
of his hand and into your hand. שמע מינה למשיכה *Shma mina
lemeshikha*, to tell you משיכה meshikha. *meshikha*. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rebbi
Yochanan*, what would רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan* say? או קנה
מאי עביד ליה *O kano mai avid lei*? What does he do
with purchase? What is that coming to tell you if not- if
it's not saying you have to take possession? היבעי ליה לכדתניא *Hibai
lei lechidetanya* וכי תמכרו ממכר *vechi simkeru mimkar* to tell you what
the ברייתא *braisa* teaches. אל תונו *Al tonu*, do not afflict, meaning
overcharge. אין לי אלא שנתאנה לוקח *Ein li ela shenis'ana lokei'ach*. I
only know that it's considered אונאה *ona'ah* if the purchaser is cheated.
He's overcharged. That's normally what we're concerned about. נתאנה מוכר mokher מנין
*Nis'ana mocher minayin*? How about if the seller is purchaser- how about
if the seller doesn't know the value of it and- and- he's
the one being cheated out, that the person is underpaid its value?
תלמוד לומר או קנה אל תונו *Talmud lomar o kano al tonu*,
or if you purchase, do not oppress. So it had to say
purchase not to say that possession is only when you, you know,
you acquire it only when you take it in possession, but to
say that the prohibition of- of charging the wrong amount applies both
to the seller and to the purchaser. Okay. אל תונו *Al tonu*.
וריש לקיש *VeReish Lakish*, and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* would say back,
תרתי שמע מינה *Tartei shma mina*. No, it says או קנה *o
kano* to tell you that the prohibition of אונאה *ona'ah* applies also
to the purchaser, and קנה מיד *kano miyad* to tell you that
the transfer occurs- that the acquisition occurs only when it transfers out
of the hand. All right. So that is the basic debate of
רבי יוחנן *Rebbi Yochanan* and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. Let's take a
look at now, just do the one more piece of this on
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תנן *Tnan*. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר כל
שהכסף בידו ידו על העליונה *Rebbi Shimon omer kol shehakesef beyado yado
al ha'elyona*. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbi Shimon* says that if- whoever
has the money in the hand, he's the one who has the
upper hand. Meaning even though the sale isn't finished until the object
is taken possession of, so- so okay. שמעון *Shimon* goes ahead and
gives me a hundred dollars to get my cow. So the sale
isn't finished yet, he doesn't have my cow. So according to the
תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*, שמעון *Shimon* or I can back out. According
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbi Shimon*, no, since I'm holding on
to the hundred dollars, I have the upper hand. I can back
out, but שמעון *Shimon* can't back out. All right, let's see how
that makes sense according to the two explanations.
מוכר mokher הוא דמצי הדר ביה *Mocher hu demati hadar bei*, I
the seller who has שמעון *Shimon*'s hundred dollars can back
out. לוקח לא מצי הדר ביה *Lokei'ach lo mati
hadar bei*, the purchaser שמעון *Shimon* cannot. אי אמרת בשלמא מעות maot
קונות *Ei amart bishlama ma'os konos*, if you say that the money
actually is what from the
תורה Torah *Torah* transfers it- because- since- meaning if you understand we
could come up with a good societal explanation why that's true
because since meaning if you understand understand that there was a rabbinic
rule to demand משיכה meshikha but from the תורה Torah מעות works
then it's possible to understand that in some cases for whatever reason
and we'll discuss the reason in a minute for some cases they
let the money work and in some cases they overrode it with
משיכה. meshikha So you could understand a position like רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon that would say that for whatever reason that you know for
the מוכר for the קונה koneh doesn't have a right to back
out. Excuse me got that right yeah the קונה doesn't have a
right to back out. He paid the money from the תורה Torah
the sale is final but the מוכר for some reason he has
the right to use to say no no no I'm going to
wait until there's משיכה. meshikha Since there's a דרבנן Derabbanan override we
could understand how you might be able to split it. I'll get
to the logic in a minute but at least you have both
systems operating so it would be possible. Okay. מתיב הדרי
ביה. Mative hadrei beih. אלא אם אמרת מעות אינן קונות Ela im
amart maot einan konot but if money is meaningless according to the
תורה Torah לוקח נמי ליהדרי ביה. lokeyach nami lihadrei beih. So how
can you have רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon giving more rights to the
guy with the money in the hand? Nothing has happened yet according
to the תורה Torah until the object is taken possession. So אמר
ליה ריש לקיש amar lei Reish Lakish Reish Lakish would say to
you אליבא דרבי שמעון לא קאמינא. aliba deRabbi Shimon lo kamina. You're
right. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who has a split and sees significance
when the money changes hands he has to be working with an
assumption that from the תורה the money is somehow is meaningful. Okay
and that has to be so for him you're right the money
works מן התורה min hatorah. משיכה meshikha is rabbinic and in this
case for some reason we split it which we'll get. But because
he gives weight to the money then you're right for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon I concede the point. כי קאמינא אליבא דרבנן Ki kamina
aliba deRabbanan I'm saying according to the Rabbis. For the Rabbis it's
all about
משיכה. meshikha Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this בשלמא
דריש לקיש היינו דאיכא בין רבי שמעון לרבנן. bishlama deReish Lakish hainu
dika bein Rabbi Shimon leRabbanan. For ריש לקיש we get what the
debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the Rabbis is. For the
רבנן Rabbanan it doesn't matter who has the money the sale isn't
final because you know they hold the only thing that matters that
matters in the תורה is משיכה meshikha and until משיכה meshikha happens
nothing has happened and you can back out. And for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds maybe we only go by
money or we go by money and משיכה meshikha and he splits
between the seller and the buyer. So we understand their debate. אלא
לרבי יוחנן מאי איכא בין רבי שמעון לרבנן? Ela leRabbi Yochanan mai
ika bein Rabbi Shimon leRabbanan? For רבי יוחנן what's at the core
of the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the Rabbis? If
they both hold כסף kesef is from the תורה and משיכה meshikha
is rabbinic what is the logic of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
a way of saying this who splits between the seller and the
buyer? So now we're going to find the answer to that thing
I put a peg in. So the גמרא Gemara says איכא בינייהו
דרב חסדא ika beinaihu deRav Chisda the position of רב חסדא Rav
Chisda דאמר רב חסדא כשם שתיקנו משיכה במוכרין כך תיקנו משיכה בלקוחין.
de'amar Rav Chisda keshem shetiknu meshikha bemokhrin kach tiknu meshikha belokkhin. רב
חסדא Rav Chisda says the same way they established משיכה meshikha for
the seller that from the seller's perspective it doesn't work until the
משיכה meshikha takes place they also established it from the buyer's perspective
that from the buyer also the sale doesn't take place until משיכה
meshikha happens meaning it's the same from both sides which makes sense.
So therefore the Rabbis hold that for both seller and buyer משיכה's
meshikha the thing that does it it doesn't matter who has the
money in its hands.
רבי שמעון לית ליה דרב חסדא Rabbi Shimon leit lei deRav Chisda
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of רב חסדא Rav Chisda רבנן
אית להו דרב חסדא Rabbanan it lehu deRav Chisda and the Rabbis
hold of it. Now it still does not exactly explain why. The
Rabbis hold the logical thing משיכה meshikha was established to override כסף
kesef it works for both the seller and buyer. But now we're
back with really not having explained it but just saying that according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you know משיכה meshikha. is only benefits
the buyer the seller can't back out excuse me only benefits the
seller the buyer I'm sorry I got that wrong. The seller it
only benefits the seller. The buyer for can't back out once
he gave money for him we leave it at the דאורייתא De'oraita
once he gave money it's done. The buyer though I'm sorry I
keep on getting that wrong. Let's try with Shimon and me. Shimon
and me. Shimon I have the money Shimon is selling me my
cow Shimon gave me I'm the seller Shimon gave me the money.
So for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon I know I have Shimon. For
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon,
they only established משיכה meshicha to the benefit of me the seller.
So because משיכה meshicha was done the buyer cannot back out of
it. משיכה meshicha is only to my benefit it solidifies it from
the buyer's perspective from the buyer's perspective.
But I as the seller I'm not bound yet by משיכה meshicha
and therefore I can still go ahead and back out. Now
so
for the buyer it goes by money he gave me the money
he's stuck and for me the seller it goes by by משיכה.
meshicha Since the משיכה meshicha didn't happen yet, I can still back
out and that's רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon. position. So that's the explanation.
They only established משיכה meshicha for the seller, not for the buyer,
but it still doesn't explain why. רש"י Rashi has a very convoluted
explanation
and תוספות Tosafot really goes a big argument with him, and part
of the question is do you get a מי שפרע mi shepara
if some accident actually did happen and the fire did break out
and there's a real good reason why you want to back out
between the משיכה and the money. But at the end of the
day, it's not really clear in the גמרא Gemara and רש"י Rashi
doesn't really have a sharp explanation about why it would work for
one side and not the other, but at the end of the
day, so we can speculate on that. But nevertheless, what the גמרא
is saying is, and let's just wrap this up, so I got
that confused a second ago, but anyway, for רבי שמעון who distinguishes
between the buyer and the seller when the money is given, for
him clearly the money is meaningful and that works with the רבי
יוחנן position that money works מן התורה. So for רבי שמעון, for
the buyer at least, the money, for the seller, I'm sorry, did
it again. For the buyer, we keep it the way it was
and the money is what finalizes it and once the money is
given the buyer cannot back out. For the seller, you need משיכה
and as long as the משיכה didn't happen the seller can still
back out. Doesn't explain why. It seemed like the whole point was
to protect the interests of the buyer, here it seems like we're
trying to protect the seller, but that's the way it is for
רבי שמעון. For the רבנן, Rabbanan, for רבי יוחנן, it's that for
the רבנן Rabbanan משיכה was established for everybody, and for ריש לקיש,
it's just that for the רבנן Rabbanan משיכה is the תורה הלכה
for everyone. Okay and that is the debate of רבי יוחנן and
ריש לקיש, to be continued tomorrow.